<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Madhikar Yoga</title><link href="https://yoga.madhikar.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://yoga.madhikar.com/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://yoga.madhikar.com/</id><updated>2024-10-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Madhikar Yoga Podcast Episode 2: One more session for managing anxiety</title><link href="https://yoga.madhikar.com/madhikar-yoga-podcast-episode-2-one-more-session-for-managing-anxiety.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-10-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2024-10-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Madhikar Yoga</name></author><id>tag:yoga.madhikar.com,2024-10-10:/madhikar-yoga-podcast-episode-2-one-more-session-for-managing-anxiety.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We kicked of a discussion about Anxiety in episode 1, &lt;a href="https://yoga.madhikar.com/madhikar-yoga-podcast-episode-1-managing-anxiety-with-yoga.html"&gt;linked here&lt;/a&gt;. We discussed various aspects of the subject. Some of the main points are summarised here. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we know, anxiety is a strong and sudden onset or a long lasting stress. This changes the function of neuro-transmitters in the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We kicked of a discussion about Anxiety in episode 1, &lt;a href="https://yoga.madhikar.com/madhikar-yoga-podcast-episode-1-managing-anxiety-with-yoga.html"&gt;linked here&lt;/a&gt;. We discussed various aspects of the subject. Some of the main points are summarised here. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we know, anxiety is a strong and sudden onset or a long lasting stress. This changes the function of neuro-transmitters in the brain and, in turn causes changes in mood resulting in fear and cold sweats. Usually, it is the result of an accidental or a sudden traumatic incident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several immediate, short-term, and long-term methods of managing stress. These methods help us to subdue, or sometimes even completely eliminate, this very uncomfortable state of mind. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remedies I speak of can be natural or medical in nature. Natural ways include: quickly seeking qualified counselling, immediately changing thought patterns and with positive mental visualisation, or turning to entertainment such as listening to soothing music or watching a movie, visiting an art museum, etc...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One could also consult doctors who may recommended doses of certain substances that temporarily dampen the mind by interfering with neurochemistry. This may be necessary in some very extreme cases, but, I am of the opinion that it is not any good way of managing anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this episode, we take advantage of one of the natural methods. We will divert and comfort the mind with meditation. This creates an immediate positive effect and gives peace-of-mind. When done with discipline it will also improve self-confidence. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, I recommend you lie comfortably in bed while listening to this episode. It is best listened to over some loud speakers with your head resting on a pillow, but feel free to use headphones if that is more convenient. Here we go!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/madhikar-yoga6/embed" height="150px" width="100%" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><category term="Podcast"></category></entry><entry><title>Podcast has moved to Spotify</title><link href="https://yoga.madhikar.com/podcast-has-moved-to-spotify.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-10-09T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2024-10-09T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Madhikar Yoga</name></author><id>tag:yoga.madhikar.com,2024-10-09:/podcast-has-moved-to-spotify.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We have decided to move the podcast for some technical reasons as many listeners were having difficulties listening to us. The good news is that we are now on Spotify! You will be able to subscribe and keep up with the podcast there. Below is a listing of all of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We have decided to move the podcast for some technical reasons as many listeners were having difficulties listening to us. The good news is that we are now on Spotify! You will be able to subscribe and keep up with the podcast there. Below is a listing of all of the episodes recorded so far. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/madhikar-yoga6/embed" height="300px" width="100%" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><category term="Announcements"></category></entry><entry><title>Madhikar Yoga Podcast Episode 1: Managing Anxiety with Yoga</title><link href="https://yoga.madhikar.com/madhikar-yoga-podcast-episode-1-managing-anxiety-with-yoga.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-09-25T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2024-09-25T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Madhikar Yoga</name></author><id>tag:yoga.madhikar.com,2024-09-25:/madhikar-yoga-podcast-episode-1-managing-anxiety-with-yoga.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Anxiety and Yoga&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the first episode of the Madhikar Yoga podcast. We are going to discuss various aspects of Yoga and how it can help us improve our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This episode deals with a problem that we all have experienced at many times in our lives, Anxiety. This …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Anxiety and Yoga&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the first episode of the Madhikar Yoga podcast. We are going to discuss various aspects of Yoga and how it can help us improve our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This episode deals with a problem that we all have experienced at many times in our lives, Anxiety. This problem is often crippling and can also affect us for prolonged periods of time. That's why we thought this would be a good topic to start with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This episode is divided in to two parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part 1: A free-form discussion about anxiety. Here we learn about what the different types of anxiety are, how to recognise them, and some simple tricks to manage anxiety - or at the very least, quickly reduce them in the moment. We also explore some theories of how anxiety is described from in Yoga. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part 2: Guided meditation. This is a recording of a short session of guided meditation and visualisation conducted by Dr. Prabhakar. We recommend listening to it several times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Part 1: What is Anxiety?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/madhikar-yoga6/embed/episodes/Episode-1-Part-1-Anxiety-and-Yoga-e2pg2lv/a-abirao5" height="150px" width="100%" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Part 2: Guided Meditation and Visualisation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before listening to this part of the podcast, we recommend you lie down in a comfortable position on your bed. You may use headphones to minimise disturbance to others, but this recording is best listened to over some loud speakers so that your head and ears stay comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe &lt;iframe src="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/madhikar-yoga6/embed/episodes/Episode-1-Part-2-Guided-Meditation-and-Visualization-e2pg2sd/a-abirb00" height="150px" width="100%" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thank you!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hope you enjoyed the discussion and the guided meditation! More episodes will follow soon.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Podcast"></category></entry></feed>